Sherman, Roger Minott Papers, 1773-1845 Ms 2
Fairfield Museum and History Center
Sherman, Roger Minott Papers, 1766-1848
Ms 2
Fairfield Museum and History Center
2.0 Linear feet (7 boxes, 3 oversize items)
Legal, financial, political papers and correspondence belonging to Fairfield lawyer and state senator Roger Minott Sherman who among many positions served as Associate Justice of the Supreme Court of Errors in Connecticut from 1839-1842.
Sherman, Elizabeth Gould, d. 1848
Sherman, Roger M. (Roger Minott), 1773-1844
Conditions Governing Access note
There are no restrictions on access to this collection.
Biographical/Historical note
Roger Minott Sherman (1773-1844), the son of the Rev. Josiah and Martha Minott Sherman, was born in Woburn, Mass. He grew up in Milford, Goshen, and Woodbridge, Connecticut and graduated from Yale in 1792. In 1796 he was admitted to the bar, married Elizabeth Gould, and set up a law practice in Norwalk. Twin sons, James M. and William G., were born in 1799. Their daughters Harriet and Eliza both died young. He moved his family to Fairfield in 1807, to a home he built on the Old Post Road still known today as the Sherman Parsonage. He continued to practice law, participated in town affairs, was elected to the State Senate, and served as Associate Justice of the Supreme Court of Errors in Connecticut from 1839-1842. Sherman’s interests extended to literature and science.
For more information on Roger Minott Sherman see:
Beers, William. (1882). A biographical sketch of Roger Minott Sherman. Bridgeport, CT.
Hamlen, B. L. (1846). "Life of the late Roger Minott Sherman." Extracted from The New Englander, Vol. IV. New Haven, CT.
This collection preceded another Roger Minott Sherman collection, Ms B96.
Scope and Contents note
This collection consists of five boxes of documents and two boxes containing seventeen assorted ledgers (account books, court docket books, plus one friendship book belonging to Elizabeth Gould Sherman).
The manuscripts and ledgers originally from the Bridgeport Public Library Historical Collections are so indicated by a [B] on the item itself.
The general contents of the collection are a broad spectrum of papers, mostly incoming, including personal, business and legal correspondence. Because R. M. Sherman was highly connected in business, legal, political and church circles, this collection contains material from and about the leaders of the times. Included in one letter from Aaron Burr in 1830 (Box III, Folder F) and an interesting English law case report (Box IV, Folder O).
The personal and business correspondence in Boxes I through III are arranged by year. Within each folder the letters are alphabetically ordered.
Boxes IV and V contain personal and business bills and receipts, deeds, depositions, dwelling agreements, insurance papers, land surveys, notes about legal cases, papers from organizations to which Robert M. Sherman belonged, petitions, promissory notes, wills, writs, summons, subpoenas and other miscellaneous personal and legal documents. Material in folders is generally arranged alphabetically.
Oversize items include a "friendship books" kept by Elizabeth Sherman between 1817 and 1833, some of Roger M. Sherman's account books and ten docket books from Count and Superior Courts dated 1800-1844.
Custodial History note
A number of items in this collection were received from the Bridgeport Public Library Historical Collections on 27 June 1979. The others are from an unknown source.
Burr, Aaron, 1756-1836; Account books--Connecticut--Fairfield.; Correspondence.; Deeds--Connecticut--Fairfield.; Depositions; Judges.; Petitions; Probate records--Connecticut--Fairfield; Receipts(financial records); Wills.; Writs--Connecticut.
- Box I: Personal correspondence, 1793-1844; 14 folders
  Other Finding Aids note
  A complete list of letter writers is available in the box.
  - Personal correspondence, incoming, 1793-1804; Folder A; 16 items
  - Personal correspondence, incoming, 1806-1812; Folder B; 14 items
  - Personal correspondence, incoming, 1813-1815; Folder C; 15 items
  - Personal correspondence, incoming, 1815-1820; Folder D; 29 items
  - Personal correspondence, incoming, 1822-1825; Folder E; 13 items
  - Personal correspondence, incoming, 1826-1831; Folder F; 17 items
  - Personal correspondence, incoming, 1832-1834; Folder G; 9 items
  - Personal correspondence, incoming, 1835-1836; Folder H; 22 items
  - Personal correspondence, incoming, 1837-1839; Folder I; 10 items
  - Personal correspondence, incoming, 1840; Folder J; 11 items
  - Personal correspondence, incoming, 1841; Folder K; 9 items
  - Personal correspondence, incoming, 1842-1843; Folder L; 14 items
  - Personal correspondence, incoming, 1844 and n.d.; Folder M; 5 items
  - Personal correspondence, outgoing, 1807-1844; Folder N; 14 items
- Box II: Business correspondence, 1794-1823; 18 folders
  A complete listing of letter writers can be found in the Box.
  - Business correspondence, incoming, 1794-1799; Folder A; 14 items
  - Business correspondence, incoming, 1800-1802; Folder B; 12 items
  - Business correspondence, incoming, 1803-1806; Folder C; 17 items
  - Business correspondence, incoming, 1807-1808; Folder D; 19 items
  - Business correspondence, incoming, 1809-1811; Folder E; 16 items
  - Business correspondence, incoming, 1812; Folder F; 12 items
  - Business correspondence, incoming, 1813; Folder G; 11 items
  - Business correspondence, 1814; Folder H; 15 items
  - Business correspondence, incoming, 1815; Folder I; 13 items
  - Business correspondence, incoming, 1816; Folder J; 16 items
  - Business correspondence, incoming, 1817; Folder K; 16 items
  - Business correspondence, incoming, 1818; Folder L; 17 items
  - Business correspondence, incoming, 1819; Folder M; 18 items
  - Business correspondence, incoming, 1820; Folder N; 14 items
  - Business correspondence, incoming, 1821; Folder O; 9 items
  - Business correspondence, incoming, 1822; Folder P; 21 items
  - Business correspondence, incoming, 1823; Folder Q; 20 items
- Box III: Business correspondence, 1825-1844; 21 folders
  A complete listing of letter writers is available in the Box.
  - Business correspondence, incoming, 1825; Folder A; 16 items
  - Business correspondence, incoming, 1826-1827; Folder B; 22 items
  - Business correspondence, incoming, 1828; Folder C; 20 items
  - Business correspondence, incoming, 1829; Folder D; 15 items
  - Business correspondence, incoming, 1830; Folder E; 24 items
  - Business correspondence, incoming, 1831; Folder F; 26 items
  - Business correspondence, incoming, 1832; Folder G; 17 items
  - Business correspondence, incoming, 1833; Folder H; 11 items
  - Business correspondence, incoming, 1834; Folder I; 11 items
  - Business correspondence, incoming, 1835; Folder J; 14 items
  - Business correspondence, incoming, 1836-1837; Folder K; 16 items
  - Business correspondence, incoming, 1838; Folder L; 12 items
  - Business correspondence, incoming, 1839; Folder M; 19 items
  - Business correspondence, incoming, 1840; Folder N; 19 items
  - Business correspondence, incoming, 1841; Folder O; 11 items
  - Business correspondence, incoming, 1842; Folder P; 11 items
  - Business correspondence, incoming, 1843-1844; Folder Q; 11 items
  - Business correspondence, no date, Folder R; 3 items
  - Business correspondence, outgoing, 1807-1844; Folder S; 27 items
  - Business correspondence, other, 1794-1835; Folder T; 11 items
- Box IV: Legal and financial papers, essays, 1766-1847; 20 folders
  A more detailed list of items is available in the Box.
  - Bills and bills receipted, incoming, 1766-1847; Folder A; 21 items
  - Card catalogues (photos) from Sterling Library at Yale, Folder B; 5 items
  - Deeds to Roger and/or Elizabeth Sherman, 1810-1837; Folder C; 21 items
  - Deeds by date, 1768-1833; Folder E; 17 items
  - Depositions, 1798-1843; Folder F; 21 items
  - Dwelling agreements from R. M. Sherman, 1812-1843; Folder G; 7 items
  - Essays and articles, 1809-1844; Folder H; 16 items
  - Financial statements, 1772-1840; Folder I
  - Household bills receipted, incoming, 1802-1817; Folder J; 26 items
  - Household bills receipted, incoming, 1818-1847; Folder K; 25 items
  - Insurance papers, 1839-1843; Folder L; 3 items
  - Land surveys and agreements, 1792-1843; Folder M; 9 items
  - Legal cases, 1794-1841; Folder N; 12 items
  - Legal cases, n.d.; Folder O; 27 items
  - Legal statements, 1803-1845; Folder P; 18 items
  - Legislative and government material, 1814-1844; Folder Q; 10 items
  - Miscellaneous, Folder R
  - Organizations and memberships, 1800-1840; Folder S; 17 items
- Box V: Legal and financial papers, 1783-1848; 7 folders
  A detailed list of items can be found inside the Box.
  - Petitions, 1806-1837; Folder A; 16 items
  - Promissory notes, 1816-1842; Folder B; 7 items
  - Stock transfers to R. M. Sherman, 1809-1834; Folder C; 23 items
  - Wills and estate distributions, 1804-1848; Folder D; 5 items
  - Wills and estate distributions, 1783-1845; Folder E; 6 items
  - Writs, summons and subpoenas, 1803-1834; Folder F; 13 items
  - Writs, summons and subpoenas, 1803-1839; Folder G; 15 items
- Box VI: Account books, 4 folders
  - Elizabeth Sherman's friendship book, 1817-1833; Folder A
  - R. M. Sherman account book, 1805-1811; Folder B
  - R. M. Sherman account books, 1824-1828, 1820-1832; Folder C; 2 items
  - R. M. Sherman account book, 1799; Folder D
- Box VII: Account and docket books, 5 folders
  - R. M. Sherman County & Superior Court dockets, 1800-1804, 1805-1809; Folder A
  - R. M. Sherman County & Superior Court dockets, 1811-1819, 1808-1810; Folder B
  - R. M. Sherman County & Superior Court dockets, 1819-1824, 1825-1832; Folder C
  - R. M. Sherman County & Superior Court dockets, 1819-1824, 1829-1836, 1837-1839; Folder D
  - R. M. Sherman account books, 1833-1844; Folder E
- Oversize Item A: R. M. Sherman account book, 1796-1803
- Oversize Item B: R. M. Sherman account book "B", 1803-1805
- Oversize Item C: R. M. Sherman account book, 1811-1820